Williams Obstetrics.
Chapter 66: Neoplastic Disorders.
Cancer Therapy In Pregnancy Cervix Uterus Ovary Breast Carcinoma BRCA1/2 MUTATIONS Thyroid Cancer.
Lymphomas.
Malignant Melanoma.
Gastrointestinal Tract Cancer.
References.
Any of the many neoplasms that affect reproductive-aged women can complicate pregnancy.
Fortunately, most encountered neoplasms are benign, and uterine leiomyomas and ovarian cysts are the most frequent.
Despite this, the incidence of malignancy approximates 1 case per 1000 to 2000 pregnancies (Korenaga, 2020; Ma, 2020).
A third are diagnosed prenatally, and the remainder within 12 months of delivery.
The distribution of some of these is shown in Figure 66-1 (de Haan, 2018).
In another report from the Cancer Research Network, breast malignancies made up 25 percent and thyroid cancers, 20 percent.
Melanoma and hematological and cervical cancers each contributed approximately 10 percent .
Figure 66-1.
Distribution of cancer in 1170 pregnant women form the International Network on Cancer, Infertility, and Pregnancy (INCIP).
During pregnancy, cancer management poses unique problems related to fetal concerns, and treatment is individualized.
Considerations include the type and stage of malignancy, the desire for pregnancy continuation, and inherent risks associated with modifying or delaying cancer treatment.
Last, adverse pregnancy outcomes have been associated in general with gravidas with cancer (Ma, 2020; Momen, 2018).
Cancer Therapy In Pregnancy.
# Surgery.
Operative procedures may be indicated to aid cancer diagnosis, staging, or therapy.
Fortunately, most surgeries that do not interfere with the reproductive tract are well tolerated by both mother and fetus .
Although many operations have classically been deferred until after 12 to 14 weeks’ gestation to minimize miscarriage risks, this probably is unnecessary.
We believe that surgery should be performed at any gestational age if maternal well-being is imperiled.
Both pregnancy and malignancy are risk factors for venous thromboembolism (VTE).
From studies of women with cancer during pregnancy, the risk of VTE is higher in pregnancy and in the postpartum period than in gravidas without a malignancy (Bleu, 2016; Greiber, 2021).
Current guidelines lack specific recommendations for pregnant women undergoing surgeries for cancer.
Thus, depending on the complexity of the planned procedure, it seems reasonable to consider prophylactic lowmolecular-weight heparin combined with elastic stockings and/or intermittent pneumatic compression .
# Diagnostic Imaging.
Sonography is a preferred imaging tool during pregnancy.
Even so, the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2019c) notes that most diagnostic radiographic procedures deliver very low x-ray doses and should not be delayed if they would directly affect therapy .
Magnetic resonance (MR) imaging can safely be performed in any trimester, but delay until after the first trimester may lower potential risks.
Gadolinium should not be used in the first trimester and should be used later in pregnancy only when the benefits overwhelmingly outweigh risks (American College of Radiology, 2021; Kanal, 2013).
Computed tomography (CT) is less often selected due to ionizing radiation, and procedure-related doses are listed in Chapter 49 (p. 874).
Thus, CT imaging is used in pregnancy most often to evaluate acute concerns that include pulmonary embolism, bowel or renal obstruction, and acute neurological events.
To enhance CT imaging, oral and intravenous contrasts may be added.
These lack known fetal harm, and postpartum breastfeeding need not be interrupted.
In pregnancy, some radioisotopes are relatively safe (Table 49-10, p. 876).
# Radiation Therapy.
Therapeutic radiation is used to treat cancers and delivers a higher radiation dose than that with diagnostic imaging.
Radiotherapy may significantly expose the fetus depending on the dose, tumor location, field size, and gestational age.
Potential adverse effects include fetal malformation, intellectual disability, growth restriction, sterility,
and carcinogenesis (Brent, 1999; Stovall, 1995).
In the 2 weeks following fertilization, exposure typically leads to chromosomal damage and embryonic death.
The next most susceptible period is during organogenesis in weeks 2 through 8, and exposure can create malformations.
These might develop above a threshold dose of 0.1 to 0.2 Gy.
During weeks 8 through 25, the fetal central nervous system is especially vulnerable.
The threshold dose for intellectual disability at 8 to 15 weeks’ gestation approximates 0.06 Gy, and at 16 to 25 weeks it is about 0.25 Gy (Kal, 2005; Otake, 1996).
After 25 weeks’ gestation, susceptibility is less, although no gestational age is considered safe for therapeutic radiation exposure.
Thus, radiotherapy to the maternal abdomen is contraindicated.
With some head and neck cancers, however, radiotherapy to supradiaphragmatic areas can be used relatively safely with abdominal shielding of the fetus .
# Chemotherapy.
Various antineoplastic drugs may be given as primary or adjunctive therapy.
Although chemotherapy often improves long-term maternal outcomes, many are reluctant to employ it during pregnancy.
Concerns for the fetus include malformations, growth restriction, intellectual disability, and the risk of future childhood malignancies.
Risks depend primarily on fetal age at exposure, and most agents are potentially detrimental in the first trimester during organogenesis.
Indeed, in one review, 14 percent of major malformations were attributable to first-trimester exposure to cytotoxic drugs .
After the first trimester, most antineoplastic drugs are without immediate obvious adverse fetal sequelae (Korenaga, 2020; Vercruysse, 2016).
Similarly, late mutagenic effects appear limited (Amant, 2015b; Cardonick, 2015).
Although not always practicable, some recommend that chemotherapy be withheld in the 3 weeks before expected delivery because neutropenia or pancytopenia might cause undue risk for maternal infection or hemorrhage.
Another concern is that neonatal hepatic and renal clearance of chemotherapy metabolites is limited .
For these reasons, most cytotoxic chemotherapy agents are contraindicated with breastfeeding .
# Molecular Therapy.
Biological agents designed to stimulate hemopoiesis are commonly used with cancer treatments.
Some of these include the granulocyte colony-stimulating factors filgrastim (Neupogen) and pegfilgrastim (Neulasta).
If required in pregnancy, limited data support the safety of these agents .
Red blood cells can be stimulated by erythropoietin alfa (Procrit), which from case reports also appears safe in pregnancy .
However, maternal hypertension is a known potential risk.
Last, for chemotherapyinduced thrombocytopenia, romiplostim and eltrombopag are thrombopoietin-receptor agonists that appear to be safe in pregnancy (Chua, 2020; Michel, 2020).
# Targeted Therapy.
The two main types of targeted therapy are monoclonal antibodies and smallmolecule inhibitors.
Both block the actions of specific enzymes, proteins, or other molecules involved in cancer cell growth .
Another is nanotherapy using drugs incorporated into encapsulated nanoparticles .
These drugs are designed to treat an ever-expanding list of cancers, and some are described in later discussions of specific tumors.
Most of these compounds are labeled by the Food and Drug Administration as class D, and data are limited regarding their pregnancy or breastfeeding effects.
Many of these drugs target tyrosine kinase, an important enzyme that regulates signaling pathways involved with cell division, differentiation, and apoptosis.
With first-trimester use, embryo toxicity or teratogenicity has been attributed to these.
Thus, use balances potential maternal benefit and potential fetal risk .
Of other agents, the monoclonal antibody trastuzumab (Herceptin) inhibits the human epidermal growth factor receptor type 2 (HER2), which some breast cancers express.
Although not teratogenic, its use in the second and third trimesters is associated with oligohydramnios, which appears to be reversible upon stopping the drug
McCormick, 2018; Zagouri, 2013b).
Because of sparse available data, other HER2 inhibitors are best avoided in pregnancy .
# Fertility and Pregnancy after Cancer Therapy.
Oncofertility is an emerging discipline to preserve fertility in young adults diagnosed with cancer .
Fertility may be diminished after chemotherapy or radiotherapy.
Counseling ideally takes place before cancer treatment, and guidelines have been developed by the American Society for Reproductive Medicine (ASRM) (2018) and other major groups (Oktay, 2018; van de Kooi, 2021).
Prior to therapy, embryo or oocyte cryopreservation is a recognized option.
Ovarian tissue cryopreservation is available in research settings (American Society for Reproductive Medicine, 2013a,b, 2014).
In addition, many cancer survivors conceive by assisted reproductive technologies (ART), which by itself has associated obstetrical risks .
If pelvic radiation is planned, surgical transposition moves ovaries and their intact primary blood supply out of the pelvis.
The ovary is then fixed to the lateral abdominal wall at a site 3 to 4 cm above the level of the umbilicus.
Metal clips are placed to help identify the ovary in future imaging .
In one review, functional preservation was reported in 65 to 94 percent, depending on radiotherapy type .
In counseling cancer survivors, evidence suggests that exposure to most radiotherapy or chemotherapy agents does not significantly raise the risk of congenital anomalies or genetic disease in their offspring (Signorello, 2012; Winther, 2012).
In those treated as children, chemotherapy does not show a consistent link to adverse obstetrical outcomes (Melin, 2015; Reulen, 2009).
Data are limited in those with cancer treated as an adult, and some studies show slightly higher rates of preterm birth and cesarean delivery (Haggar, 2014; Stensheim, 2013).
Prior abdominopelvic radiation more convincingly affects neonatal outcomes, including elevated rates of abortion, low birthweight, stillbirth, and preterm birth (Signorello, 2006, 2010; Winther, 2008).
Radiation may reduce uterine volume, thin the endometrium, and impair uterine blood flow (Critchley, 1992; van de Loo, 2019).
Radiotherapy directed to the uterus and given at a younger age shows greater effects .
# Placental Metastases.
Tumors infrequently metastasize to the placenta.
The most common types are malignant melanomas, leukemias, lymphomas, and breast cancer .
Placentas from pregnancies in all women with cancer should be sent for histological evaluation.
Tumor cells are usually confined within the intervillous spaces, and fetal metastases are rare (Al-Adnani, 2007; Rubrecht, 2020).
Reproductive Tract Neoplasms.
Benign neoplasms of the reproductive tract are common and include leiomyomas, ovarian tumors, and endocervical polyps.
Cancer in these organs may also complicate pregnancy, and of these, cervical neoplasia makes up most (de Haan, 2018).
# Cervix.
Endocervical Polyp These are overgrowths of endocervical stroma covered by epithelium.
They typically appear as single, red, elongated fleshy masses of variable size that extend outward from the endocervical canal.
Usually benign, they can bleed and can be a source of Pap test results reported as atypical glandular cells of undetermined significance—AGUS.
With removal and histological polyp evaluation, dysplasia is diagnosed in up to 0.5 percent, and cancer is found in approximately 0.1 percent .
Few formal data guide management in pregnancy.
Small asymptomatic lesions may be left alone to slough during delivery or puerperal remodeling.
Removal and histological evaluation is reasonable if malignancy is suspected or if bleeding is troublesome.
For most, the polyp is grasped with ring forceps and twisted repeatedly about its base to strangulate feeding vessels.
With repeated twisting, the base narrows and avulses.
Monsel paste, which is ferric subsulfate, can be applied with pressure to the stalk stub for hemostasis.
A thick-pedicle polyp may infrequently warrant surgical ligation and excision.
Cervical Neoplasia Pregnancy provides an
opportune time to screen for cervical intraepithelial neoplasia (CIN) and invasive cervical cancer.
With Pap test screening, pregnancy status should be noted on the requisition form as cytological interpretation may be influenced by normal pregnancy-associated changes.
Presence of decidual cells and, less often, an Arias-Stella reaction are examples.
The latter gives an appearance of endocervical gland hyperplasia, which can make differentiating this from truly atypical glandular cells difficult.
Current screening guidelines apply to both nonpregnant women and gravidas (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2021b; U.S. Preventive Services Task Force, 2018).
Recommendations for average-risk women include: (1) no screening until age 21, (2) cytology alone every 3 years in those aged 21 to 29 years, and (3) in women aged ≥30 years, three options are suitable.
These are human papillomavirus (HPV) plus cytology, termed co-testing, every 5 years; primary HPV testing every 5 years; or cytology every 3 years.
Higher-risk women with altered immune systems include women with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection, systemic lupus erythematosus, organ transplant, or immunosuppressant medication use .
Others include those with past CIN or prior early cervical cancer or in utero diethylstilbestrol (DES) exposure.
Affected women are screened earlier and more often using current guidelines for HIV-affected individuals .
Germane to gravidas aged ≤30 years, these guidelines recommend Pap test screening at the time of initial HIV diagnosis and then yearly.
Once three consecutive Pap test findings are normal, screening may be spaced to every 3 years.
Co-testing is not recommended.
For those aged >30 years, similar Pap testing is applied.
Co-testing is suitable for this group, and if negative, the next test can repeated in 3 years.
Human Papillomavirus.
This virus infects cervical epithelia.
The infection usually clears, but in some, the virus may promote benign, premalignant, or cancerous neoplastic growth.
The prevalence of HPV infection in pregnant women approximates 15 percent (Hong, 2013; Liu, 2014).
Of the many HPV serotypes, several are associated with high-grade squamous intraepithelial (HSIL) lesions and invasive cancer.
Serotypes 16 and 18 are preeminent.
HPV testing targets only high-risk types associated with cervical neoplasia, and identification of types 16 or 18 prompts colposcopic evaluation.
There is no indication for low-risk HPV testing.
Serotypes HPV 6 and 11 are linked with benign maternal genital warts.
Congenital HPV infection resulting from vertical transmission, which is mother to fetus/newborn passage, beyond transient skin colonization is rare.
Still, conjunctival, laryngeal, vulvar, or perianal warts present at birth in the neonate or that develop within 1 to 3 years of birth are most likely due to perinatal exposure to these maternal HPV serotypes .
Importantly, cesarean delivery does not lower the risk of neonatal laryngeal papillomatosis.
The clear link between HPV infection and cervical neoplasia led to development of approved vaccines that reduce cervical cancer risk .
Only one vaccine is currently available in the United States.
Gardasil 9 is a nonavalent HPV vaccine (9vHPV) against HPV types 6, 11, 16, 18, 31, 35, 45, 52, and 58.
This vaccine is not administered during pregnancy and is compatible with breastfeeding .
Abnormal Cytology and Histology.
The incidence of abnormal cervical cancer screening test results and their management is similar for gravidas and nonpregnant women.
Current 2019 management consensus guidelines from the American Society of Colposcopy and Cervical Pathology focus on the individual’s risk for CIN 3 or cervical cancer, rather than on specific screening results .
Management has become complex and derives from large database analyses.
Factors include the abnormal cytology and HPV results, age, and previous screening results.
As a result, algorithms now calculate the best clinical approach to abnormal screening test results
www.asccp.org/management-guidelines).
In overview, certain cytological abnormalities and HPV test results warrant colposcopy, and the main goal during pregnancy is to exclude invasive cancer.
Thus, lesions suspicious for high-grade disease or cancer are biopsied.
Endocervical sampling, endometrial biopsy, and treatment of preinvasive lesions are unacceptable during pregnancy.
Women with histologically confirmed CIN from biopsy during pregnancy are allowed to deliver vaginally.
Further evaluation is planned at least 4 weeks postpartum.
Alternatively, for clinical findings with higher cancer risk, repeat colposcopy and cytology/HPV testing are performed at intervals no more frequently than 12 weeks.
Biopsy is repeated only if a lesion appears worse or invasive cancer is suspected .
Postpartum reassessment may reveal lesions missed previously due to either cervical changes of pregnancy or advancing lesion severity.
Instead, CIN regression is common during pregnancy or puerperium.
In one study of 1079 pregnant women with cervical dysplasia in which biopsy correlated with colposcopic findings, 61 percent of lesions reverted to normal postpartum .
In another study, lesions regressed postpartum in 70 percent of women with CIN 2 or 3.
However, 7 percent of CIN 2 lesions progressed to CIN 3, but no lesion advanced to invasive cancer .
In another study of 77 women with carcinoma in situ (CIS) diagnosed antepartum, a third had postpartum regression of their lesion, two thirds had persistent CIS, and only two women had microinvasive cancer on cone biopsy after delivery .
Adenocarcinoma in situ (AIS) is managed in a manner similar to CIN 3 .
Thus, unless invasive cancer is identified, treatment of AIS is not recommended until 6 weeks postpartum.
Referral to a gynecologist with advanced colposcopic skills is recommended .
Cervical Conization.
If invasive epithelial lesions are suspected, conization is indicated and may be done with loop electrosurgical excisional procedure (LEEP) or by cold-knife conization.
However, the epithelium and underlying stroma within the endocervical canal cannot be extensively excised without the risk of membrane rupture.
Logically, residual disease is common.
Of 376 cone biopsies during pregnancy, residual neoplasia was later found in 43 percent of subsequent specimens .
In another series, nearly 10 percent of 180 pregnant women required transfusion after conization .
Thus, if possible, conization is avoided in pregnancy because of its higher risks for abortion, membrane rupture, hemorrhage, and preterm delivery.
Women with CIN treated before pregnancy may also encounter pregnancy complications.
First, distal cervical stenosis is uncommon but may follow conization, LEEP, or laser surgery.
Cervical stenosis almost always yields during labor.
A so-called conglutinated cervix may undergo almost complete intrapartum effacement without dilation.
Spontaneous dilation usually promptly follows firm pressure with a fingertip, although instrumented dilation or cruciate incisions may be required.
Second, preconceptional cold-knife conization is associated with cervical insufficiency and preterm birth.
However, the relationship between preterm birth and LEEP continues to be debated (Castanon, 2012; Conner, 2014; Stout, 2015).
The size of tissue excised seems to be directly related to adverse outcomes .
Invasive Cervical Cancer This cancer is found in approximately 1 in 1200 to 10,000 pregnancies (Bigelow, 2017; McCormick, 2018).
The diagnosis is confirmed with biopsies taken during colposcopy, with conization, or from a grossly abnormal lesion.
Of the histological types, squamous cell carcinomas account for 75 percent, whereas adenocarcinomas compose the remainder .
Cancers may appear as exophytic or endophytic growth; as a polyp, papillary tissue, or barrel-shaped cervix; or as focal ulceration or necrosis.
A watery, purulent, foul, or bloody discharge may be present.
The sensitivity of a single Pap test is poor.
Thus, biopsy with Tischler forceps is warranted for suspicious lesions.
Abnormal tumor vessels may
cause heavier than expected biopsy-site bleeding, which is usually controlled by Monsel paste and pressure.
Historically, cervical cancer was solely staged clinically.
The current staging system now incorporates radiological and surgical evaluation .
Lymph node metastasis is now also included in staging.
Allowable components of clinical staging are cold-knife conization, pelvic examination under anesthesia, cystoscopy, intravenous pyelogram (or this portion of MR imaging can be used), proctoscopy, and chest radiography.
Notably, physiological pregnancy changes may limit physical assessment of cancer extent, which is more likely to be underestimated in gravidas.
Specifically, induration of the broad ligament base, which characterizes tumor spread beyond the cervix, may be less prominent due to cervical, paracervical, and parametrial pregnancy-induced softening.
MR imaging can be used without gadolinium contrast to ascertain involvement of the urinary tract, parametrium, and lymph nodes .
Management and Prognosis.
Cervical cancer treatment in pregnant women is individualized, and factors include the clinical stage, fetal age, and individual desire to continue pregnancy.
Stage IA1 is termed microinvasive disease and describes lesions with deepest invasion <3 mm .
If diagnosed by cone biopsy, treatment follows guidelines similar to those for intraepithelial disease.
In general, continuation of pregnancy and vaginal delivery are considered safe, and definitive therapy is reserved until 6 weeks postpartum.
In contrast, cancer with greater invasion demands relatively prompt therapy.
During the first half of pregnancy, immediate treatment is advised by most, but the decision whether to continue pregnancy is a factor.
During the latter half of pregnancy, the risk of early delivery versus delayed treatment are weighed .
In two studies with a total of 40 women past 20 weeks’ gestation with either stage I or stage IIA carcinoma, delayed treatment was considered reasonable in women without bulky lesions (Takushi, 2002; van Vliet, 1998).
Another option is to complete staging using laparoscopic lymphadenectomy and to delay treatment if metastases are excluded (Alouini, 2008; Favero, 2010).
In a metaanalysis, preoperative neoadjuvant chemotherapy with platinum derivatives was found to be promising for treatment in pregnancy .
Although surgical therapy and radiation are equally effective, radical hysterectomy plus pelvic lymphadenectomy is the preferred treatment for invasive cervical cancer in most young women with stage I and early stage IIA lesions.
Disadvantageously, radiotherapy for cervical cancer destroys ovarian and possibly sexual function and frequently causes intestinal and urinary tract injury.
In 49 women with pregnancy-associated stage IB cancer, a 30-percent severe complication rate accompanied radiotherapy compared with that of only 7 percent with radical surgery .
With surgery before 20 weeks’ gestation, radical hysterectomy is usually performed with the fetus in situ.
In later pregnancy, however, hysterotomy and delivery is often performed first .
Figure 66-2.
Radical hysterectomy specimen with invasive cervical squamous cell carcinoma.
With radical hysterectomy, the parametrium and 2 to 3 cm of vagina are excised to help achieve a tumor-free resection.
Reproduced with permission from Dr. Debra L. Richardson.
Although rarely selected during pregnancy, Ungár and colleagues (2006) performed abdominal radical trachelectomy before 20 weeks’ gestation for stage IB1 cancer in five pregnant women.
One cases series describes four women with stage IA1 adenocarcinoma at 16 to 23 weeks’ gestation treated with laser conization, and all delivered at term .
For more advanced-stage cancer, radiotherapy is given.
External beam radiation in early in pregnancy typically leads to spontaneous abortion.
If miscarriage does not ensue, curettage is performed.
During the second trimester, spontaneous abortion may not promptly occur and may necessitate hysterotomy in up to a fourth of cases.
This is selected because labor
induction or dilation and evacuation may pose serious hemorrhage risks from the cancer.
Pregnancy does not negatively affect cervical cancer prognosis, and survival outcomes are similar for pregnant and nonpregnant women (Amant, 2014; Mogos, 2013).
For both of these groups, the overall 5-year survival rate approximated 80 percent in a case-control study of 44 women with pregnancy-associated cervical cancer (van der Vange, 1995).
Delivery Adverse prognostic effects from vaginal delivery through a cancerous cervix are unknown.
For this reason, the mode of delivery is controversial, especially for small, early-stage lesions.
In some cases of bulky or friable tumors, hemorrhage from the cancer may complicate vaginal delivery.
Also, recurrences in the episiotomy scar have been reported .
Thus, most favor cesarean delivery.
Pregnancy after Radical Trachelectomy Radical trachelectomy for stage IB1 and IB2 cervical cancer before conception is one fertility-sparing option.
During the typically vaginal procedure, the cervix is amputated at the level of the internal os, and a permanent-suture cerclage is placed around the isthmus to support future pregnancies.
The uterine isthmus is then reconstructed to the vagina.
Following this, women continue to menstruate, and conception can occur naturally.
Because of the permanent cerclage, a classical cesarean incision is required for delivery.
Evidence suggests that cervical length <13 mm at 20 weeks’ gestation is associated with preterm birth <34 weeks .
In a systematic review of 2566 women after radical trachelectomy for earlystage cancer, the 5-year overall maternal survival rate was 97 percent .
The pregnancy rate was 24 percent, and the live-birth rate was 75 percent.
# Uterus.
Leiomyomas Also known as myomas and somewhat erroneously called fibroids, uterine leiomyomas are common benign smooth-muscle tumors.
Their incidence during pregnancy approximates 2 percent, but the cited range depends on the frequency of routine sonography and population characteristics (Qidwai, 2006; Stout, 2010).
In one study of 4271 women, the first-trimester myoma prevalence was highest in black women—18 percent—and lowest in whites —8 percent .
Leiomyomas vary in location and may develop as submucosal, subserosal, or intramural growths.
Less often, these develop in the cervix or broad ligament.
Rare parasitic types obtain their blood supply from adjacent structures such as the omentum.
In another rare manifestation— leiomyomatosis peritonealis disseminata—numerous, small, benign subperitoneal smooth-muscle tumors mimic carcinomatosis but often regress after pregnancy.
In general, progesterone is considered the critical mitogen for uterine leiomyoma growth.
In turn, estrogen functions to upregulate and maintain progesterone receptors .
In pregnancy, progesterone’s effect on myoma growth is unpredictable, and tumor size may grow, regress, or remain unchanged (Laughlin, 2009; Neiger, 2006).
Especially during pregnancy, these masses can be confused with other pelvic masses, and sonographic imaging is indispensable .
Once diagnosed, myomas do not require sonographic surveillance unless associated complications are anticipated.
With unclear sonographic findings, MR imaging may be necessary and ideally performed after the first trimester.
Figure 66-3.
Leiomyoma imaging.
A. In this sagittal view from transvaginal sonography, a large uterine leiomyoma (calipers) displays heterogeneous echoes and occupies the fundus.
This mass lies adjacent to an early first-trimester gestational sac (G) that shows a yolk sac.
B. MR imaging at 16 weeks’ gestation shows a large leiomyoma (L) in the posterior uterine segment and cervix, which fills the pelvis.
Associated ureteral compression and hydronephrosis required placement of a percutaneous nephrostomy tube.
At term, planned cesarean delivery was done due to obstruction of the birth canal.
B = bladder; F = fetus; P = placenta.
Symptoms.
Most leiomyomas are asymptomatic, but acute or chronic pain or pressure may develop, especially with large masses
Doğan, 2016).
For chronic pain, nonnarcotic analgesic drugs usually suffice.
More acutely, some myomas can outgrow their blood supply and hemorrhagic infarction follows, which is termed red or carneous degeneration.
Clinically, acute focal abdominal pain and tenderness are preeminent and often accompanied by leukocytosis or low-grade fever.
Thus, tumor degeneration may be difficult to differentiate from other sources of acute abdominal pain.
Sonography aids diagnosis, but close observation is requisite because an infarcted myoma is essentially a diagnosis of exclusion.
Uncommonly, preterm labor is stimulated by associated inflammation.
Symptoms from a degenerated myoma usually abate within a few days.
In severe cases, observation may be needed to exclude a septic cause.
Although surgery is rarely needed during pregnancy, myomectomy in highly selected cases has yielded good outcomes.
Of 23 reported cases, women were 14 to 20 weeks’ gestation, and in almost half, surgery was performed because of pain (Celik, 2002; De Carolis, 2001).
Except for one loss immediately following surgery at 19 weeks, most underwent cesarean delivery at term.
Occasionally, a pedunculated subserosal myoma will undergo torsion with subsequent painful necrosis.
Laparoscopy or laparotomy can be used to ligate the stalk and resect the necrotic tumor.
That said, we believe that surgery should be limited to tumors with a discrete pedicle that can be easily clamped and ligated.
Pregnancy Complications.
Myomas have been associated with several complications that include preterm labor, placental abruption, fetal malpresentation, obstructed labor, cesarean delivery, and postpartum hemorrhage.
In a review of pregnancy outcomes in 2065 women with myomas compared with unaffected gravidas, placental abruption and breech presentation were each increased fourfold; first-trimester bleeding and dysfunctional labor, twofold; and cesarean delivery, sixfold .
In a report of 301 women with myomas, the preterm birth risk was 2.5-fold higher than in unaffected women .
Another study reported an eightfold increased second-trimester abortion risk in affected women .
Factors most important in determining morbidity in pregnancy are myoma number, size, and location (Ciavattini, 2015; Jenabi, 2018; Lam, 2014).
If the placenta is adjacent to or implanted over a leiomyoma, the risks for abortion, preterm labor, placental abruption, and postpartum hemorrhage are all increased.
Retroplacental myomas are also associated with fetal-growth restriction .
Myoma-related bleeding may stem from miscarriage, preterm labor, placenta previa, and placental abruption.
Rarely, bleeding results from a submucous myoma that has prolapsed from the uterus and into the cervix or vagina.
In this case, although heavy or persistent bleeding may require earlier intervention, the stalk, if accessible, can be ligated vaginally near term to avoid avulsion during delivery.
Tumors in the cervix or lower uterine segment may obstruct labor .
Despite these complications, Qidwai and associates (2006) reported a 70-percent vaginal delivery rate even in women in whom myomas measured ≥10 cm.
These data argue against empirical cesarean delivery, and we allow a trial of labor unless myomas clearly obstruct the birth canal.
If cesarean delivery is indicated, uterine malrotation, which can be caused by a bulky lateral myoma, should be excluded by palpation of the fundus prior to hysterotomy .
Myomas are generally left alone.
Specifically, because of enucleation-associated hemorrhage, myomectomy during cesarean delivery is discouraged.
Exceptions include recalcitrant intraoperative bleeding or a myoma that prohibits hysterotomy closure.
With cesarean delivery in one study, mean hemoglobin levels dropped in those with myomas, but the transfusion rate was not increased .
Importantly, cesarean hysterectomy may be technically difficult because of lateral ureteral displacement by the masses.
Figure 66-4.
Cesarean delivery performed because of a large leiomyoma in the lower uterine segment.
A classical vertical uterine
incision, seen to the left of the myoma, was required for delivery of the fetus.
Fortunately, myomas rarely become infected .
When infection develops, it usually is postpartum, especially if the tumor is located immediately adjacent to the implantation site .
They also may become infected with an associated septic abortion or with myoma perforation by a sound, dilator, or curette.
Fertility Considerations.
Despite their relatively high prevalence in young women, their negative effect on fertility is unclear.
Moreover, evidence from one systematic review was inconclusive to support myomectomy for intramural or subserosal myomas to improve fertility .
As an exception, the American Society for Reproductive Medicine (2017) describes fair evidence for hysteroscopic myomectomy of submucous myomas to improve clinical pregnancy rates.
In a systematic review of nearly 1400 pregnancies, myomas were not associated with a higher miscarriage rate .
Instead of an infertility indication, some women may elect myomectomy to treat bleeding or pressure symptoms yet still desire fertility preservation.
Importantly, after myomectomy, the gravid uterus can rupture either before or during labor .
Management is individualized, and review of the prior operative report is prudent.
If resection resulted in a defect into or immediately adjacent to the endometrial cavity, cesarean delivery is usually done before labor.
Timing of cesarean delivery is individualized, and the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2021b) cites between 370/7 and 386/7 weeks’ gestation.
Uterine artery embolization of myomas is another option for women seeking symptom relief yet desiring fertility preservation .
Women so treated have higher rates of miscarriage, cesarean delivery, and postpartum hemorrhage.
The Society of Interventional Radiology considers myoma embolization relatively contraindicated in women who plan future pregnancies .
Even so, myoma embolization does not harm ovarian reserve .
Endometrial Lesions With endometriosis, studies have recently focused on a link with adverse obstetrical outcomes (Stephansson, 2009; Zullo, 2017).
However, data are complicated by heterogeneity regarding disease stage and location, use of ART, and analysis methodologies .
Despite this, an association with placenta previa is the most consistent.
Occasionally, an endometrioma can develop after delivery from endometrial tissue implanted within laparotomy or episiotomy scars.
Pfannenstiel incisions carry greater susceptibility than vertical ones .
These form a palpable mass and can cause cyclical localized pain.
Endometriomas within an ovary are discussed in the next section.
Adenomyosis is traditionally found in late reproductive life and beyond.
Its acquisition may be at least partially related to disruption of the endometrial-myometrial border during sharp curettage for abortion .
In one systematic review, miscarriage, poor fetal growth, preeclampsia, placenta previa, and preterm delivery were associated risks .
Endometrial carcinoma is an estrogen-dependent neoplasia also usually found in women aged >40 years and thus seen only rarely with pregnancy .
Of 27 cases that were identified during pregnancy or within the first 4 months postpartum, most were found in first-trimester curettage specimens .
These are usually early-stage, welldifferentiated adenocarcinomas for which treatment consists primarily of total abdominal hysterectomy and bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy.
For nonpregnant women, surgical management of early endometrial cancer is also the standard.
However, to preserve fertility potential in a well-counseled woman with early-stage, well-differentiated, endometrioid endometrial cancer, treatment with oral or intrauterine progestin therapy can be used to prompt tumor regression .
Notably, live birth rates are low, and a large percentage requires ART for conception .
Moreover, recurrences and deaths have been reported .
# Ovary.
Ovarian masses found during pregnancy are common.
Incidences vary depending on the frequency of prenatal sonography, the
ovarian size threshold, and study site designation as tertiary or primary care.
Thus, the incidence of ovarian masses not surprisingly ranges from 1 in 100 to 2000 pregnancies (Bacalbaşa, 2020; Korenaga, 2020).
Of ovarian malignancies, the incidence in the California Cancer Registry was 1 case in 19,000 pregnancies .
The most frequent types of ovarian masses are corpus luteum cysts, endometriomas, benign cystadenomas, and mature cystic teratomas (dermoid cysts).
In one series of 53 endometriomas diagnosed in the first trimester, a fourth each remained stable or increased in size, and a third shrank .
Mature cystic teratomas enlarge infrequently during pregnancy.
Rarely, a teratoma may express N-methyl-D-aspartate (NMDA) receptors within the tumor’s neural-tissue component.
Antibodies form against these receptors within the tumor and then attack similar-looking receptors in the brain.
In one case, a pregnant woman developed encephalitis from these antibodies .
Because pregnant women are usually young, malignant tumors and those of low malignant potential are proportionately uncommon.
One study found that 1 percent of 9375 ovarian masses were frankly malignant and that another 1 percent were of low malignant potential .
In surgically excised masses, rates of malignancy are higher, vary from 4 to 13 percent, and probably reflect a greater preoperative concern for cancer .
Diagnosis Most ovarian masses are asymptomatic.
Some cause pressure or chronic pain, and acute abdominal pain may be due to torsion, rupture, or hemorrhage.
Rarely, blood loss is sufficient to cause hypovolemia.
Ovarian masses are usually detected during routine prenatal sonography or during imaging for other indications, including symptom evaluation.
For complicated anatomy, MR imaging can be used without contrast.
Cancer antigen 125 (CA125) is a tumor marker, and levels are frequently elevated with ovarian malignancy.
Importantly, in early pregnancy and early puerperium, CA125 levels are normally elevated, possibly from the decidua.
From the second trimester until term, levels are not normally higher than those in the nonpregnant woman (Appendix, p. 1229) (Korenaga, 2020; Szecsi, 2014).
With severe preeclampsia, however, concentrations are abnormally elevated .
Other tumor markers that have been used for diagnosis or posttreatment surveillance in pregnancy include human chorionic gonadotropin (hCG), alpha-fetoprotein (AFP), inhibins A and B, carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA), and the multimarker OVA1 test .
Complications Torsion and hemorrhage are significant complications of adnexal masses.
Torsion usually causes acute constant or episodic lower abdominal pain and tenderness that is accompanied frequently by nausea and vomiting.
Transvaginal sonography (TVS) often aids diagnosis, and an adnexal mass is typically comorbid.
With color Doppler, absent flow strongly correlates with torsion.
However, minimal or early twisting may compromise only venous flow, thus leaving the arterial supply intact.
Other sonographic signs are ovarian stromal edema; follicle displacement to the ovarian periphery; free cul-de-sac fluid; the whirlpool sign, which displays twisted vessels of the involved pedicle; and the follicular ring sign (Moro, 2020; Yatsenko, 2021).
This last sign is a 1- to 2-mm echogenic rim around antral follicles and may reflect edema and engorged capillaries.
If torsion is suspected, laparoscopy or laparotomy is warranted.
Contrary to prior teaching, most now recommend untwisting to save the ovary .
Concerns for thrombus release and pulmonary embolism have been allayed .
A grossly necrotic adnexum is removed.
With a salvageable ovary, within minutes of untwisting, congestion is relieved but the blue-black color typically persists.
Figure 66-5.
Ovarian torsion at term.
The patient underwent cesarean delivery, and the left uteroovarian pedicle was untwisted.
Reproduced with permission from Dr. C. Edward Wells.
If the adnexum is deemed viable, there are options.
First, an associated neoplasm is resected.
However, ovarian cystectomy in an edematous
ovary may be technically difficult, and adnexectomy may be necessary.
Less often, cystectomy may be delayed for low-risk lesions to allow easier enucleation following edema resolution .
Second, oophoropexy, especially for a second case of torsion, can minimize recurrence risk .
Techniques described include shortening of the uteroovarian ligament with a running stitch or fixing the uteroovarian ligament to the posterior uterus, the lateral pelvic wall, or the round ligament .
The most common cause of ovarian hemorrhage follows rupture of a corpus luteum cyst.
Symptoms mirror those of hemoperitoneum, and diffuse lower abdominal pain is usual.
TVS shows blood in the cul-de-sac and a collapsed ovarian cyst remnant (Fig. 12-5, p. 224).
If the diagnosis is certain and symptoms abate, observation and surveillance is usually sufficient.
Concern for ongoing bleeding will typically prompt surgical evaluation.
If the corpus luteum is removed before 10 weeks’ gestation, progestational support is recommended to maintain the pregnancy.
Suitable regimens include: (1) micronized progesterone (Prometrium), 200 or 300 mg orally once daily; (2) 8-percent progesterone vaginal gel (Crinone), one premeasured applicator vaginally daily, plus micronized progesterone, 100 or 200 mg orally once daily; or (3) intramuscular 17-hydroxyprogesterone caproate, 150 mg.
The first two regimens are given until 10 completed weeks.
For the last, if given between 8 and 10 weeks’ gestation, only one injection is required immediately after surgery.
If the corpus luteum is excised between 6 and 8 weeks’ gestation, two additional doses should be given 1 and 2 weeks after the first.
Asymptomatic Adnexal Mass During Pregnancy Most of these are incidentally found, and decisions include necessity and timing of resection.
A cystic benign-appearing mass measuring <5 cm often requires no additional antepartum surveillance.
Early in pregnancy, this is likely a corpus luteum cyst, which typically resolves by the early second trimester.
For cysts ≥10 cm, the risk of malignancy, torsion, or labor obstruction is substantial, and surgical removal is reasonable.
Tumors between 5 and 10 cm are carefully evaluated by TVS coupled with color Doppler and possibly MR imaging.
Simple-appearing cysts can be managed expectantly with sonographic surveillance (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2016; Schmeler, 2005).
Resection is done if cysts grow, display malignant qualities, or become symptomatic.
Those with classic findings of endometrioma or mature cystic teratoma may be resected postpartum or during cesarean delivery for obstetrical indications.
Figure 66-6.
Sonographic characteristics of common adnexal masses in pregnancy.
A. A simple hemorrhagic cyst with smooth walls and an internal reticular pattern is characteristic of a physiological corpus luteum cyst.
B. Homogeneous cystic mass with diffuse internal low-level echoes suggestive of an endometrioma or hemorrhagic corpus luteum.
C. Mature cystic teratoma (dermoid cyst) appears as a complex adnexal cyst.
On the right side, hyperechoic lines and dots represent hair in both longitudinal and transverse planes.
At the central superior aspect of this cyst, a mural nodule—the Rokitansky protuberance—is seen.
A fat (right side)-fluid (left side) level is another common finding with these tumors.
On the other hand, if sonographic findings suggest cancer, prompt resection is indicated .
Nodules, papillary excrescences, solid components, or thick, vascular septa within the mass or ascites are suggestive findings .
In one review of 563 masses in pregnancy, approximately half were simple, and the other half complex .
Among simple masses, 1 percent were malignant, and of complex masses, 9 percent were cancerous.
Approximately 1 in 1000 pregnant women undergoes surgical exploration for an adnexal mass .
In general, we plan resection at 14 to 20 weeks’ gestation because most masses that will regress will have done so by this time.
Laparoscopic removal is ideal (Naqvi, 2015; Sisodia, 2015).
Importantly, the
American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2016) recommends consultation with a gynecological oncologist for elements implicating cancer that include a very elevated CA125 level, a nodular or fixed pelvic mass, ascites, evidence of metastasis, or ultrasound findings suggesting malignancy.
Pregnancy-Related Ovarian Tumors One group of ovarian masses results directly from the stimulating effects of various pregnancy hormones on ovarian stroma.
These include pregnancy luteoma, hyperreactio luteinalis, and ovarian hyperstimulation syndrome.
Pregnancy Luteoma.
This is a rare, benign ovarian neoplasm that arises from luteinized stromal cells and classically raises testosterone levels (Hakim, 2016; Irving, 2011).
Up to 25 percent of affected women will be virilized, and of these affected women, nearly half of their female fetuses will have some degree of virilization.
However, most mothers and their fetuses may be unaffected because the placenta rapidly converts testosterone to estrogen (Kaňová, 2011).
In typical cases, an adnexal mass along with maternal virilization will prompt sonography and measurement of testosterone and CA125 levels.
Luteomas are variably sized, appear solid, may be multiple or bilateral, and may be complex because of internal hemorrhage .
Concerns for malignancy may be further investigated with MR imaging (Kao, 2005; Tannus, 2009).
Total testosterone levels are increased, but notably, levels in normal pregnancy can be substantially elevated (Appendix, p. 1231).
Differential diagnoses include granulosa cell tumors, thecomas, Sertoli-Leydig cell tumors, Leydig cell tumors, stromal hyperthecosis, and hyperreactio luteinalis.
Generally, luteomas do not require surgical intervention unless torsion, rupture, or hemorrhage complicate these .
Tumors spontaneously regress during the first few months postpartum, and androgen levels drop precipitously following delivery .
Lactation may be delayed a week by hyperandrogenemia .
Recurrence in subsequent pregnancies is rare.
Hyperreactio Luteinalis.
In this condition, one or both ovaries develop multiple, large theca-lutein cysts, typically after the first trimester.
Cysts are caused by luteinization of the follicular theca interna layer, and most are stimulated by exceptionally high hCG levels .
Thus, they are more common with gestational trophoblastic disease, twins, fetal hydrops, and other conditions with increased placental mass .
Maternal but not fetal virilization may develop .
Serum testosterone levels are not predictive of maternal virilization .
Sonographically, these ovarian tumors have a “spoke wheel” pattern (Fig. 13-3, p. 238) .
If the diagnosis is confident, and unless complicated by torsion or hemorrhage, surgical intervention is not required.
These masses resolve after delivery.
Few data allow prediction of recurrence in a subsequent pregnancy, but in one case report, a woman had hyperreactio with three pregnancies .
Ovarian Hyperstimulation Syndrome.
This is typified by multiple ovarian follicular cysts accompanied by increased capillary permeability.
It most often is a complication of ovulation-induction therapy for infertility, although it rarely may develop in an otherwise normal pregnancy.
Its etiopathogenesis is thought to involve hCG stimulation of vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) expression in granulosa-lutein cells .
This causes greater vascular permeability that can lead to ascites, pleural or pericardial effusion, hypovolemia with acute kidney injury, and hypercoagulability.
Serious complications are renal dysfunction, adult respiratory distress syndrome, ovarian rupture with hemorrhage, and VTE.
Unlike hyperreactio lutealis, virilization is absent .
Management is outlined by the American Society for Reproductive Medicine (2016).
Treatment is primarily supportive to maintain vascular volume and prevent VTE.
In severe cases, paracentesis can be helpful.
Ovarian Cancer Malignancies of the ovary are the leading cause of death from genital-tract cancers in all women .
Still, the incidence of ovarian malignancy only
ranges from 1 case in 20,000 to 50,000 births (Eibye, 2013; Smith, 2003).
Of those found in pregnancy, 75 percent are early-stage cancers that carry a 5-year survival rate between 70 and 90 percent .
The types of malignancy are also markedly different in gravidas compared with those in older women.
In pregnant women, these are, in decreasing order of frequency, germ cell and sex cord-stromal tumors, low-malignant-potential tumors, and epithelial cancers .
Pregnancy apparently does not alter the prognosis of most ovarian malignancies.
Management is similar to that for nonpregnant women, with the usual proviso that it may be modified depending on gestational age.
Thus, if frozen-section histopathological analysis verifies malignancy, surgical staging is done with careful inspection of all accessible peritoneal and visceral surfaces (Bacalbaşa, 2020).
Peritoneal washings are taken for cytology, biopsies are obtained from the diaphragmatic surface and peritoneum, omentectomy is completed, and pelvic and infrarenal paraaortic lymph nodes are sampled, if accessible.
If disease is advanced, bilateral adnexectomy and omentectomy will decrease most tumor burden.
In early pregnancy, hysterectomy and aggressive surgical debulking procedures may be elected.
In other cases, minimal debulking described in the previous paragraph is done, and the operation is terminated.
In some cases of aggressive or large-volume disease, chemotherapy can be given during pregnancy while awaiting pulmonary maturation.
Monitoring maternal CA125 serum levels during chemotherapy is not accurate in pregnancy .
Preventively, increasing parity is one known factor (Fortner, 2019; Huang, 2020).
A metaanalysis also found that prior miscarriage or abortion lowered risk .
Of modifiable factors, combination oral contraceptives and breastfeeding lower ovarian cancer rates (Babic, 2020; Havrilesky, 2013; Iversen, 2018).
Discussed in Chapter 39 (p. 682), rates of some ovarian cancers may decline following tubal interruption and perhaps salpingectomy.
# Adnexal Cysts.
Paratubal and paraovarian cysts either are distended remnants of the paramesonephric ducts or are mesothelial inclusion cysts.
One autopsy series in nonpregnant women cited an incidence of 5 percent .
The most common paramesonephric cyst is the hydatid of Morgagni, which is pedunculated and typically dangles from one of the fimbria.
Although these may undergo torsion, other complications are rare, and most are identified during cesarean delivery or puerperal sterilization.
In these instances, they can simply be excised or drained by creating a large window in the cyst wall.
Neoplastic paraovarian cysts are rare, sonographically and histologically resemble tumors of ovarian origin, and rarely are of borderline potential or frankly malignant .
# Vulva and Vagina.
Preinvasive disease in young women—vulvar intraepithelial neoplasia (VIN) and vaginal intraepithelial neoplasia (VAIN)—are seen more often than invasive disease and are commonly associated with HPV infection.
As with cervical neoplasia, these premalignant conditions are treated after delivery.
Cancer of the vulva or vagina is generally a malignancy of older women, and thus, these are rarely associated with pregnancy (Amant, 2019; Korenaga, 2020).
Even so, any suspicious lesion is biopsied.
Most are squamous cell cancers, and treatment is individualized according to the clinical stage and depth of invasion.
In a review of 23 cases, investigators concluded that radical surgery for stage I disease was feasible during pregnancy—including in the last trimester .
It appears that vaginal delivery is not contraindicated if vulvar and inguinal incisions are well healed.
In late pregnancy, resection and definitive therapy can often be delayed due to these tumors’ typically slow progression .
Other vulvar cancer types and vaginal malignancies are rare in pregnancy and mainly the subjects of case reports (Korenaga, 2020; Matsuo, 2009).
Breast Carcinoma.
Breast cancer incidence in women aged 25 to 40 years has been rising since the 1930s (American
Cancer Society, 2021; Lima, 2020).
It has an overall relatively high frequency in younger women and is the most frequent cancer complicating pregnancy (see Fig. 66-1) (Alfasi, 2019; de Hann, 2018).
From the Nationwide Inpatient Sample, the incidence approximated 1 case in 15,000 births .
Postponed childbearing was considered partially responsible for the increase in pregnancy-associated breast cancer in Sweden and Denmark (Andersson, 2015; Eibye, 2013).
And, as more women choose to delay childbearing, the frequency of associated breast cancer is certain to rise.
Genetic mutations underlie some breast cancer cases, and these are discussed in that section (p. 1174).
# Diagnosis.
More than 90 percent of gravidas with breast cancer have a palpable mass, and greater than 80 percent of cases are self-reported .
In pregnancy, clinical assessment, diagnostic procedures, and treatment of women with breast tumors are often slightly delayed .
This is partially attributed to pregnancy-induced growth of breast tissue that obscures masses.
Breast mass evaluation does not differ from that for nonpregnant women (Loibl, 2015; McCormick, 2018).
Thus, any suspicious breast mass should be pursued to diagnosis.
Pragmatically, a palpable discrete mass can be biopsied or excised.
To distinguish between a solid and cystic lesion, sonography has high sensitivity and specificity .
Mammography is appropriate if indicated, and the fetal radiation risk is negligible—0.04 mGy—with appropriate shielding .
But, because breast tissue is denser in pregnancy, mammography has a falsenegative rate of 35 to 40 percent .
If the decision to biopsy is uncertain, MR imaging may be used.
To better classify imaging findings for breast masses, the American College of Radiology (2013) developed the Breast Imaging-Reporting and Data System—BI-RADS.
Suitable for sonography, mammographic, and MR imaging results, the intent is to communicate an individual woman’s risk of developing breast cancer .
Table 66-1.
American College of Radiology: Breast Imaging Reporting and Data Systems—BI-RADSa Cystic breast lesions are simple, complicated, or complex.
Simple cysts do not require special management or monitoring, but they may be aspirated if symptomatic.
Complicated cysts show internal echoes during sonography, and they sometimes are indistinguishable from solid masses.
These are typically aspirated, and if the sonographic abnormality does not resolve completely, a core-needle biopsy is usually performed.
Complex cysts have septa or intracystic masses seen sonographically.
Because some breast cancer may form complex cysts, excision is usually recommended.
For solid breast masses, evaluation uses the triple test, that is, clinical examination, imaging, and core needle biopsy.
If all three suggest a benign lesion or if all three suggest a breast cancer, the test is considered concordant.
A concordant benign triple test is ≥99-percent accurate, and breast lumps in this category can be followed by clinical examination alone.
Most masses in pregnancy have these three reassuring features.
In contrast, if any of the three assessments suggests malignancy, the mass should be excised.
# Management.
With breast cancer, a limited search of the most common metastatic sites is completed.
For most, this includes a chest radiograph, liver sonography, and skeletal MR imaging (Becker, 2016; Krishna, 2013).
MR imaging can also evaluate the abdomen, pelvis, and brain.
Treatment of breast cancer includes an obstetrician, breast surgeon, and medical oncologist.
Initially, desires for pregnancy continuation are addressed, and data indicate that pregnancy interruption does not influence the course or prognosis of breast cancer .
With pregnancy continuation, treatment in general mirrors that for nonpregnant women.
Important caveats are that chemotherapy and surgery are postponed to the second trimester, and adjuvant radiotherapy is withheld until after delivery .
Delay should be avoided as the risk of metastases increases with every few months by 5 to 10 percent .
Surgical treatment
may be definitive.
In the absence of metastatic disease, either a wide excision or a modified or total mastectomy—each with axillary node staging—can be performed .
Staging by sentinel lymph node biopsy and lymphoscintigraphy with technetium-99m is safe.
Breast reconstruction, if desired, is typically delayed until after delivery .
That said, one small series showed good results in 10 pregnant women who underwent immediate reconstruction after mastectomy .
Chemotherapy is usually given with both positive- and negative-node breast cancers.
In premenopausal women, survival rates with this approach are improved, even if lymph nodes are cancer free.
For node-positive disease, multiagent chemotherapy is begun if delivery is not anticipated within several weeks.
Cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin, and cisplatin are currently used .
If an anthracycline-based agent such as doxorubicin is used, pretherapy maternal echocardiography is performed because of associated cardiotoxicity .
Good maternal and perinatal results have been reported (Freret, 2020; McCormick, 2018).
Immunotherapy for breast cancers is now commonplace.
Trastuzumab (Herceptin) is a monoclonal antibody to the HER2/neu receptor, which is found in approximately a third of invasive breast cancers .
The drug is not recommended in pregnancy.
This is because HER2/neu is strongly expressed in fetal renal epithelium, and trastuzumab has been linked with miscarriage, fetal renal failure and related oligohydramnios, and preterm birth (Amant, 2010; Azim, 2010).
The effects of pregnancy on the course of breast cancer and its prognosis are complex.
Breast cancer is more aggressive in younger women, but whether it is more aggressive during pregnancy in these same women is debatable .
Clinically, most studies indicate little difference in overall survival rates with pregnancy-associated breast cancer compared with similarly aged and staged nonpregnant women .
Other reports note worse overall survival rates with pregnancy-associated breast cancer .
These investigators do conclude, however, that later disease stages are more prevalent in pregnant women.
Because breast cancer is usually found at a more advanced stage in pregnant women, the overall prognosis is diminished .
The aggregate of studies published after 1990 indicate that up to 60 percent of pregnant women have concomitant axillary node involvement at diagnosis.
And although, stage for stage, the 5-year survival rate is comparable in pregnant and nonpregnant women, the more advanced stages that are typical of pregnant women worsen their prognosis (Kuo, 2019; Zemlickis, 1992).
# Pregnancy Following Breast Cancer.
After breast cancer treatment, chemotherapy will render some women infertile, but childbearing options were noted earlier (p. 1164).
For those who become pregnant, long-term maternal survival rates are not adversely affected (Averette, 1999; Lambertini, 2019).
One metaanalysis found that for women with early breast cancer, pregnancy that occurs 10 months after diagnosis may, in fact, confer a survival benefit .
Breastfeeding does not adversely alter the course.
In women successfully treated for breast cancer, recurrence is a concern.
Because recurrences are more common soon after treatment, it seems reasonable to delay conception for 2 to 3 years.
Hormonal contraceptive methods are contraindicated, and a copper-containing intrauterine device is an excellent method for many.
That said, women with breast cancer who subsequently conceive do not appear to have diminished survival rates .
Those who developed breast cancer within 10 years of delivery have and increased risk for metastases .
Importantly, tamoxifen, which may be used long-term following initial therapy, is a teratogen.
Discontinuation 2 months prior to conception is recommended .
BRCA1/2 MUTATIONS Hereditary breast and ovarian cancer (HBOC) syndrome yields a susceptibility to either one or both of these two cancers in individuals with recognized gene mutations .
BRCA1 and BRCA2 mutations are preeminent, but others are associated.
Table 66-2.
Some Genes
Associated with Hereditary Cancers Preventively, cancer screening, chemoprevention, prophylactic surgery, and preimplantation testing are options.
First, ovarian cancer screening with TVS or serum CA125 levels is not routinely recommended .
For breast cancer, surveillance in those aged 25 to 29 years is clinical breast examination (CBE) performed by a provider once or twice yearly plus annual breast MR imaging.
For older individuals, yearly MR imaging and mammography are alternated every 6 months.
For women with BRCA1 and BRCA2 gene mutation, combination oral contraceptives (COC) are recognized chemoprevention for ovarian cancer .
COC effects on breast cancer risk are conflicting, and studies show no risk or modest increased risk .
For breast cancer chemoprevention, tamoxifen can lower cancer risk in those with BRCA2 defects .
Prophylactic bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy (BSO) is recommended after childbearing in those aged 35 to 40 years with BRCA1 defects and aged 40 to 45 years in those with BRCA2 mutations .
BSO or mastectomy also decreases breast cancer risk in these women (Kotsopoulos, 2016; Li, 2016; Rebbeck, 2009).
BRCA1/2 genes are transmitted in an autosomal dominant fashion.
In those planning pregnancy, affected women may elect preimplantation genetic testing of blastocysts .
However, with an established pregnancy, prenatal testing poses ethical concerns regarding pregnancy termination for a mutation that may not lead to cancer.
Currently, testing for conditions that do not accrue until adulthood are discouraged by the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020a,b).
Regarding parity, protective benefits for breast cancer in women with either BRCA defect show conflicting data (Kotsopoulos, 2018; Pan 2014; Rieder, 2015; Toss, 2017).
For ovarian cancer, parity lowers rates for women with BRCA1 but not BRCA2 mutations .
Women with either BRCA mutation who undergo induced abortion do not have an elevated breast cancer risk .
Breastfeeding conveys a protective effect against breast cancer in those with BRCA1 defects but not BRCA2 mutations.
It lowers ovarian cancer rates for those with either mutation (Kotsopoulos, 2012; 2020).
Among those with either BRCA mutation, a breast cancer diagnosis during pregnancy does not lower survival rates compared with similarly affected but not pregnant women .
After breast cancer treatment, women with either BRCA defect who pursue pregnancy do not experience increase pregnancy complication rates.
Moreover, disease-free or overall survival rates are not worsened (Lambertini, 2020; Valentini, 2013).
Thyroid Cancer.
Palpable thyroid nodules are detected in 4 to 7 percent of the population, and management is found in Chapter 61 (p. 1098).
Approximately 10 percent are malignant .
In pregnancy, thyroid cancer incidence approximates 10 cases per 100,000 births (Spiegel, 2019; Sullivan, 2019).
With this diagnosis, pregnancy termination is not necessary.
Primary therapy is partial or subtotal thyroidectomy ideally done during the second trimester.
Most lesions are well differentiated, and delayed treatment is acceptable .
For aggressive tumors, however, prompt surgical treatment is recommended.
Postoperatively, replacement thyroxine is given.
A higher risk for VTE is reported for these women .
In some thyroid cancer types, radioiodine is used for primary or postoperative treatment.
This is contraindicated in both pregnancy and lactation for several reasons.
First, iodine-131 transferred transplacentally is avidly trapped by the fetal thyroid gland to cause hypothyroidism.
Second, during lactation, the breast also concentrates a substantial amount of iodide.
This may pose neonatal risk due to radioiodine-contaminated milk ingestion and raise maternal cancer risk from significant breast irradiation.
To limit maternal exposure, a delay of 3 months between lactation and thyroid ablation will more reliably ensure complete breast involution .
In women with thyroid cancer who ultimately receive iodine-131 doses, pregnancy should be avoided for 6 months to 1 year.
This time ensures
thyroid function stability and permits confirmation of cancer remission .
Lymphomas.
# Hodgkin Disease.
This lymphoma is probably B-cell derived and is cytologically distinguished from other lymphomas by Reed–Sternberg cells.
Of cancers in pregnancy, lymphomas are common, and gestational rates are rising because of delayed childbearing (see Fig. 66-1) .
In one review from the Nationwide Inpatient Sample, the incidence of Hodgkin lymphoma approximates 1 case in 12,400 births .
In more than 70 percent of these cases, lymph nodes painlessly enlarge at sites above the diaphragm, that is, in the axillary, cervical, or submandibular chains.
Approximately one third of patients have fever, night sweats, malaise, weight loss, or pruritus.
Diagnosis is by histological examination of involved nodes .
The Lugano staging system is applied to Hodgkin and other lymphomas .
For staging, pregnancy limits the use of some radiographic studies, but at minimum, chest radiography, abdominal imaging with sonography or MR imaging, and bone marrow biopsy are completed .
MR imaging is excellent for evaluating thoracic and abdominal paraaortic lymph nodes.
Table 66-3.
Lugano Classification Staging System for Hodgkin and Other Lymphomas The current trend for nonpregnant individuals is to administer chemotherapy for all stages of Hodgkin disease.
In pregnancy, for early-stage disease in the first trimester, options include pregnancy termination or observation until after 12 weeks’ gestation and then multiagent chemotherapy (Eyre, 2015; McCormick, 2018).
For most advanced-stage disease after the first trimester, cycles of doxorubicin, bleomycin, vinblastine, and dacarbazine are given.
In general, postponement of therapy until fetal maturity is achieved seems justifiable only when the diagnosis is made late in pregnancy.
Women with Hodgkin lymphoma have a higher incidence of VTE (ElMessidi, 2015; Horowitz, 2016).
Also, in our experiences, the gravidas— even after they are “cured”—are inordinately susceptible to infection and sepsis.
Active antineoplastic therapy only raises this vulnerability.
The overall prognosis with Hodgkin lymphoma is similar to that for nonpregnant women, and 5-year survival rates exceed 90 percent .
Pregnancy does not adversely affect the cancer course of this lymphoma, and pregnancy outcomes are not generally adversely affected.
For women with disease in remission, pregnancy does not stimulate relapse .
# Non-Hodgkin Lymphomas.
Although usually B-cell tumors, non-Hodgkin lymphomas can also be T-cell or natural-killer-cell neoplasms.
Their biology, classification, and treatment are complex.
They are associated with viral infections, and their incidence has risen sharply at least partly because 5 to 10 percent of persons with HIV infection develop lymphoma.
Other associated viruses include Epstein-Barr and hepatitis C viruses and human herpes virus 8.
Some of these lymphomas are aggressive, and survival rates vary with the type of cell line involved.
Non-Hodgkin lymphomas are infrequent during pregnancy .
They also are staged according to the Lugano system.
If diagnosed in the first trimester, pregnancy termination followed by multiagent chemotherapy is recommended for all but indolent or very early disease.
These less aggressive forms may be observed in the first trimester, and then full treatment given in the second.
One regimen is rituximab plus the CHOP combination of cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin (hydroxydaunorubicin), vincristine [Oncovin], and prednisone.
In a study of 80 pregnant women with this regimen, the 3-year survival rate was 73 to 96 percent .
Burkitt lymphoma is an aggressive B-cell tumor associated with EpsteinBarr virus infection.
Prognosis is poor, and treatment is multiagent chemotherapy.
In an earlier review of 19 women whose pregnancies were complicated by this lymphoma, 17 died within a year of diagnosis .
# Leukemias.
These malignancies generally arise either from lymphoid tissues— lymphoblastic or lymphocytic leukemias, or from bone marrow—myeloid leukemias.
They can be acute or
chronic.
Adult leukemias are more prevalent after age 40 but still are among the most common malignancies of young women (see Fig. 66-1).
In two large registries, the incidence was 1 case in 40,000 to 50,000 births (Nolan, 2020; Smith, 2003).
In a review of 72 pregnancies complicated by leukemia from 1975 until 1988, 44 had acute myelogenous leukemia; 20 had acute lymphocytic leukemia; and eight had one of the chronic leukemias .
Nolan and colleagues (2020) cite similar proportions.
Acute leukemias almost always cause marked peripheral blood count abnormalities, and often the white blood cell count is elevated with readily recognizable circulating blast cells.
The diagnosis is made from bone marrow biopsy.
With current multiagent chemotherapy, remission during pregnancy is common, and termination does not further improve the prognosis.
In some cases, pregnancy termination before viability may simplify management of an acutely ill woman.
Abortion is a consideration in early pregnancy to avoid potential chemotherapy teratogens.
One is all-trans-retinoic acid, also known as tretinoin, which causes retinoic acid syndrome (Li, 2020; Santolaria, 2020).
Tyrosine kinase inhibitors are another teratogenic group (p. 1163) .
Other than these caveats, treatment of gravidas with leukemia is similar to that for nonpregnant women.
Acute myeloid leukemia is treated without delay .
After induction chemotherapy, postremission maintenance therapy is mandatory to prevent a relapse, which is then usually treated with stem-cell transplantation.
If allogeneic stem-cell transplantation is indicated, early delivery is considered.
With some chronic leukemias, it may be possible to delay therapy until after delivery .
As with lymphoma, infection and hemorrhage are significant complications that should be anticipated in women with active disease.
Most descriptions of leukemia treatment in pregnancy are single cases or small series (Routledge, 2018; Sanz, 2015).
In one review of 58 cases, 75 percent were diagnosed after the first trimester .
Half were acute myelogenous leukemia, which had a remission rate of 75 percent with chemotherapy.
Only 40 percent of these pregnancies resulted in a live birth .
In a more recent report of 92 pregnant women with acute promyelocytic leukemia, 91 percent had a complete remission .
Malignant Melanoma.
These most often originate from melanocytes in a preexisting nevus.
Lesions most often develop in fair-skinned whites and commonly in childbearingaged women.
Pigmented lesions that change in contour or height or show discoloration, bleeding, or ulceration should prompt biopsy .
In some population studies, melanoma is the most frequent malignancy complicating pregnancy (Andersson, 2015; Bannister-Tyrrell, 2015).
The reported incidence ranges from <1 to 3 cases per 1000 births (Cottreau, 2019; Eibye, 2013).
Many are treated outpatient and thus not entered into tumor registries.
Staging is clinical.
Stage I is a melanoma with no palpable lymph nodes; in stage II, lymph nodes are palpable; and in stage III, distant metastases are identified.
For patients with stage I, tumor thickness is the single most important predictor of survival.
The Clark classification includes five levels of involvement by depth into the epidermis, dermis, and subcutaneous fat.
The Breslow scale measures tumor thickness and size, in addition to invasion depth.
Primary surgical treatment for melanoma is determined by the stage and includes wide local resection, sometimes with extensive regional lymph node dissection.
The American Academy of Dermatology recommends sentinel lymph node mapping and biopsy using technetium-99m–sulfur colloid, which has a calculated fetal dose of 0.014 mSv or 0.014 mGy .
Routine regional node dissection reportedly improves survival rates in nonpregnant patients with microscopic metastases.
For gravidas, an algorithm is proposed that begins with resection of the primary tumor under local anesthesia but postpones sentinel lymph node biopsy until postpartum .
Although prophylactic chemotherapy or immunotherapy is
usually avoided during pregnancy, it may be given if indicated by tumor stage and maternal prognosis.
In most cases of distant metastatic melanoma, treatment is at best palliative.
Stage-for-stage, survival is equivalent between pregnant and nonpregnant women (Driscoll, 2016; Johansson, 2014).
In two studies, half of pregnant women presented with an advanced stage (de Haan, 2017; Sawyers, 2020).
Placentas are submitted for histological evaluation to exclude metastasis (p. 1164).
Therapeutic abortion does not improve maternal survival rates.
Clinical stage is the strongest determinant of survival, and women with deep cutaneous invasion or regional node involvement have the worst prognosis.
Approximately 60 percent of recurrences will manifest within 2 years, and 90 percent by 5 years.
Thus, most recommend that pregnancy be avoided for 3 to 5 years after surgical resection.
Interim contraception can include combination oral contraceptives, as they do not appear to have adverse cancer effects .
Gastrointestinal Tract Cancer.
Carcinomas of the colon and rectum are the third most frequent cancer in all women in the United States .
Their incidence in pregnancy is rising because of delayed childbearing .
Even so, colorectal tumors are uncommon before age 40.
An approximate incidence of 1 case in 150,000 deliveries was derived from the California Cancer Registry .
In another report, however, the incidence approximated 1 case in 13,000 pregnancies .
Of colorectal carcinomas in pregnant women, 80 percent arise from the rectum.
In one review, only 41 cases in pregnancy were colon cancers located above the peritoneal reflection .
The most frequent symptoms are abdominal pain, distention, nausea, constipation, and rectal bleeding.
If symptoms of colon disease persist, digital rectal examination, stool tests for occult blood, and colonoscopy are done.
Some gastrointestinal (GI) tract cancers are found because of metastases to the ovary.
These Krukenberg tumors are tumor-laden ovaries from another, often GI, primary and carry a bleak prognosis .
Colon cancer treatment in gravidas mirrors that for nonpregnant women.
Without evidence of metastatic disease, surgical resection is preferred, but most pregnant women have advanced lesions .
During the first half of pregnancy, hysterectomy is not necessary to perform colon or rectal resection, and thus, therapeutic abortion is not mandated.
During later pregnancy, therapy may be delayed until fetal maturation.
However, bowel hemorrhage, obstruction, or perforation may force surgical intervention.
Gastric and esophageal cancers are rare in pregnancy.
Despite this, persistent unexplained upper GI symptoms should be prompt upper abdominal sonography and perhaps endoscopy.